A Guide to the Carr-Cary Family Papers
University of Virginia Library
Special Collections, University of Virginia Library, #1231
Carr-Cary Family Papers 1785-1839
University of Virginia. Library. Special Collections Dept. Alderman Library University of Virginia Charlottesville, Virginia 22903 USA
1231
ca. 285 items
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Collection is open to research.
Acquisition Information
These papers were purchased for the Tracy W. McGregor Collection by the University of Virginia Library, from Mrs. Fairfax Harrison, Fauquier County, Virginia, on September 1, 1941.
Scope and Content
This collection consists of the papers of the Carr family of " Carrsbrook", Albemarle County, and the Cary family of " Carysbrook, " Fluvanna County, Virginia, 1785-1839, ca. 285 items (2.5 Hollinger boxes, 1 linear foot), including chiefly correspondence, but also manuscripts of obituaries, poetry, and debates, and financial documents. The papers include correspondence between Peter Carr(1770-1815), nephew of Thomas Jefferson, Hester "Hetty" Smith Stevenson Carr(1767-1834), George Pitt Stevenson(d.1819), Dabney S. Carr(1802-1854), Maria Jefferson Carr(1804-1825), Jane Margaret Carr Cary(1809-1903), Wilson Miles Cary(1806-1877), Wilson Jefferson Cary(1784-1823), and Virginia Randolph Cary(1786-1852), with other members of the Jefferson, Randolph, Carr, and Cary families.
All Thomas Jefferson correspondence has been transferred to the Thomas Jefferson Papers and is not listed in this guide. The Jefferson letters are included in the calendar
The Jefferson Papers of the University of Virginia
compiled by Constance E. Thurlow and Francis L. Berkeley, Jr. available in the Special Collections Reading Room and on the Special Collections web page under Digital Resources & Exhibitions -Guides to the Collections.
Topics include family and social news of Charlottesville, Virginia, and Baltimore, Maryland, agricultural matters and plantation life; relationships between slaves and their owners; family advice, education and study of law; the increasing financial distress of the period and other financial matters of the family; religious thought; local and national politics; scattered references to the University of Virginia and Thomas Jefferson; with genealogical notes by Wilson Miles Cary.
Topics also include proposed and subsequent sale of Carrsbrook; the sale, hire, and purchase of family slaves; Hetty Carr's move to Baltimore; a fight between Charles Lewis Bankhead and Thomas Jefferson Randolph and its after effects; John Addison Carr's career in the navy; concern for dental care; the controversial proposal of either a lottery ora subscription for the financial relief of Thomas Jefferson; and travel to Florida. The papers also contain correspondence, 1793-1807, of Thomas Mann Randolph(1768-1828, son-in-law of Thomas Jefferson, concerning agricultural and social matters; the possible engagement of John Leslie as a tutor for the Randolph family; a letter, 1802, from Thomas Mann Randolph to Peter Carr concerning his plans to respond to James Thomson Callender's accusation against Thomas Jefferson, and his decision not to do so; and a letter, 1826, from Thomas Jefferson Randolph (1792-1875) concerning Thomas Jefferson's death and desire for keeping his father from misusing money from Jefferson's estate.
The papers also contain a letter, 1797, from George Washington commenting on the divisive nature of politics and on political attacks aimed at him; a letter, 1800, from James Monroe regarding the hire of slaves and financial matters; a statement, 1814, by Anne Cary Randolph Bankhead on Thomas Jefferson Randolph's courtship and marriage to Jane Hollins Nicholas(1798-1871); an obituary, 1815, of Peter Carr by William Wirt; two student essays by Peter Carr; and poems by Virginia Randolph Cary.
Financial documents consist of receipts for payments of fees for Peter Carr at William & Mary College; receipts for payments of fees related to the education of D. Terrell and George P. Stevenson; Peter Carr's account with Hollins & McBlair of Baltimore; a receipt for blacksmith work; Hetty Carr's memorandum concerning money due her from Robert Carter Nicholas from a plantation in Louisiana; accounts of Mrs. Virginia Cary; and an account of the estate of Wilson J. Cary.
Sources for information about the Carr & Cary families include:
The Virginia Carys
by Fairfax Harrison,
The Carr Family Records
by Edson I. Carr, and
The Carrs of Albemarle
a University of Virginia History Thesis by Elizabeth Dabney Coleman.
Item Listing
- John Leslie (1766-1832), Professor of Mathematics at Edinburgh, Scotland, to Thomas Mann Randolph, 1788-1807; 7 ALS (Box Box 1)
  [advises further practical study in England, mentioning the mines of Derbyshire, the canals & works of the Duke of Bridgewater, the pottery methods of Mr. Wedgwood, the libraries at the University of Oxford, and the natural history specimens and antiquities in the museums of London, and suggests some books to read (1788 May 12); anxiously inquires if he has heard anything from Thomas Jefferson on the subject of his own possible immigration to America to continue as Randolph's teacher (1788 Jun 22); informs Randolph of his terms for employment in Virginia (1788 Aug 2); refers to his stay in Virginia in 1789, his happiness at the news of Randolph's marriage, his connection to the Wedgwood family, his paper
  Observations on Electrical Theories
  , encouragement to complete the natural history of Virginia which his father-in-law had sketched (1792 Sep 27), all these letters are bound together; regrets at leaving the Randolph family, request for seeds to be sent to him in Scotland, and his impressions of Philadelphia (1789 Jun 16); his stay at Etruria, Staffordshire with the Wedgwoods and the marriage of Randolph (1790 Jul 23); and his letter of introduction for John Wilson, mentioning the conflict between Great Britain and the United States (1807 Aug 28)]
- Peter Carr to his mother, Mrs. Martha (Jefferson) Carr (1746-1811), 1789 May 3 (Box Box 1)
  [assures her of his affection and tells of his plans to accompany Captain Lilly with Mrs. Griffin, to New York City, where he hopes to see many of the important men of the new Congress, including James Madison and his uncle, Thomas Jefferson, after his return from France]
- Thomas Mann Randolph to Peter Carr, 1793 Jun 26 (Box Box 1)
  [suggests that William try to buy lime in Richmond, James is setting out for Varina Grove with the horses for Mr. Hughes and will also have the deed for Edgehill to present to Colonel Randolph for his acknowledgment of the signature, and mentions the necessity of hiring labor to help in his wheat fields]
- Thomas Mann Randolph to Peter Carr, 1793 Dec 15 (Box Box 1)
  [mentions his child Ann Cary (1791-1826), and the upcoming Christmas party at Beverly Randolph's]
- Martha Jefferson Randolph to Peter Carr, 17[96?] Nov 28 (Box Box 1)
  [congratulates him upon his approaching marriage (in June 1797?) to Hester Smith Stevenson]
- George Washington to John Langhorne, 1797 Oct 15 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses political divisions and the attacks made upon those in government, perhaps referring to the John Nicholas affair]
- Dabney Carr to unknown correspondent, 17[?] (Box Box 1)
  [discusses how Dr. Walker has violated the principle that the public interest should be preferred to private advantage]
- Richard Terrell to Peter Carr, 1800 May 30 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses his suit in the District Court, Lexington, Kentucky, over land in the forks of the [Elkhorn?] River, and their hope that Thomas Jefferson will win the election]
- Peter Carr to his sister, Mary Carr, 1800 Jul 24 (Box Box 1)
  [the murder of [Samuel] Burch of Charlottesville, Virginia, by George Carter, who was angry over not being allowed in the Burch home to see Betsy Minor; the natural death of Tom Fleming; the hiring of slave woman Rose by Mr. Lott; the schooling of his stepson, George P. Stevenson, who has a private tutor at the home of Colonel Nicholas, and the sickness of little Jefferson (died in infancy)]
- James Monroe to Peter Carr, 1800 Aug 19 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses his financial arrangements to meet his obligations to "some Jews in Richmond," which involve [the slave hire of?] two girls presently with their grandmother "at the mountain,"and Lucy who has served her term of three years with Mr. Carr]
- Cradock Vaughan to Peter Carr, 1801 Sep 19 (Box Box 1)
  [dancing master concerning his account for George P. Stevenson]
- John Hollins to Peter Carr, 1801 Sep 25 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses Hetty's (Hester Stevenson Carr) deed for the wharf property and procuring a carriage from Philadelphia for Carr]
- John Hollins to Peter Carr, 1801 Nov 12 (Box Box 1)
  [mentions the deed for the warehouse property in Baltimore and offers condolences to Hetty (Hester Stevenson Carr) and Peter Carr on the loss of their son, Jefferson]
- Thomas Mann Randolph to Peter Carr, 1802 Dec 24 (Box Box 1)
  [refers to the charges against Thomas Jefferson by James Thomson Callender]
- John Wayles Eppes (1773-1823) to Peter Carr, 1803 Jan 3 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses politics and the Republican party, the report of the Ways & Means Committee, his desire for Meriwether Jones to become the commissioner of loans, news of the Spanish troops disembarking at New Orleans, his expectation that the Louisiana Territory will pass from the French prefect to the United States without difficulty, and the two remaining matters before Congress being the creation of a Louisiana Territory government and the impeachment of a drunken judge]
- George P. Stevenson to Peter Carr, 1803 Apr 28 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses horses, family matters, and a duel between Mr. Windom Grimes, of Richmond, and Mr. Terrell, with Wilson J. Cary (1784-1823), Peter Carr's nephew, as his second]
- William H. Cabell to Peter Carr, 1805 Nov 22 (Box Box 1)
  [asks Peter Carr to pay his brother, Dabney Carr (1772-1837) a debt for a horse incurred by Cabell, if it is convenient]
- Peter Carr to Mary Carr, 1806 Dec 31 (Box Box 1)
  [mentions the sale of slave woman, Nelly and her two children, to Mr. Rothwell for six hundred dollars and the hire of [Sary]
- George P. Stevenson to Peter Carr, 1807 Jan 1 (Box Box 1)
  [politics in the Virginia General Assembly and the eloquence of several speeches, especially T.L Preston of Rockbridge]
- George P. Stevenson to Peter Carr, 1808 Jan 25 (Box Box 1)
  [reports on his studies at Warren, Virginia, and his boarding at Mr. White's]
- P. R. Gilmer to Peter Carr, 1808 Jul 15 (Box Box 1)
  [regrets that Rice has beaten him in the election, supposes James Madison will succeed Thomas Jefferson in the presidency and mentions the Embargo]
- W. L. Stone to Peter Carr, 1809 Apr 21 (Box Box 1)
  [advice to Carr on campaigning as a candidate in the state Senate, which he supports]
- George P. Stevenson to Peter Carr, 1810 May 8 (Box Box 1)
  [asks concerning the possibility of selling his property in Augusta County, Virginia]
- Peter Johnston to Peter Carr, 1811 Feb 7 (Box Box 1)
  [begs Carr to come and visit him before he moves to southwest Virginia]
- Peter Carr to Mary Carr, 1811 Oct 6 (Box Box 1)
  [assures her he has written to Mr. Divers concerning Louisa, [a slave?]
- Jane B. Cary (1767-1840) to Mary Carr, 1811 Oct 26 (Box Box 1)
  [describes her travel, searching for items in the Richmond stores for her sister Mary, and the letter has a handwritten genealogical chart o f the Cary family]
- Jane B. Cary to Mary Carr, 1811 Dec 24 (Box Box 1)
  [William Newsum (1785-1828) gone to Norfolk on business; includes some additional genealogical notes re the Carr family]
- Peter Carr to his niece, Martha J. Terrell (1796-1860), 1812 Feb 1 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses his children, the progress of his school, marriage of George P. Stevenson, and the election of Dabney Carr as Chancellor of the Winchester District]
- Peter Carr to George P. Stevenson, 1812 May 24 (Box Box 1)
  [expresses his disappointment that George and Eliza have postponed their trip to Carrsbrook, uncertainty over placing his son Dabney, with George in his counting house if they do not plan to visit very often, and his anxiety that they are going to set up housekeeping for themselves before George has finished his apprenticeship; also mentions the land in Augusta County, Virginia]
- Peter Carr to Joseph J. Monroe, 1812 Jun 12 (Box Box 1)
  [requests he forward any letter of Carr's in his possession]
- Extracts from a letter from an unknown correspondent to "Brother Woods" concerning Peter Carr, "G.W.," and Colonel John Nicholas, possibly to be used in a lawsuit, [1812?] (Box Box 1)
- Philip Norborne Nicholas to Wilson J. Cary, 1813 May 1 (Box Box 1)
  [forwards the legal opinion of [John] Wickham about money due from the Fairfax estate and holds the other papers for Cary or his agent]
- Wilson Cary Nicholas to Peter Carr, 1813 Jun 10 (Box Box 1)
  [gives his advice concerning a controversy with Mr. N[elson] and Mr. Eustis involving Carr over an appointment]
- Statement by Mrs. Ann C. Bankhead, 1814 Jun 21 (Box Box 1)
  [writes concerning a visit of Thomas Jefferson Randolph to Warren, Albemarle County to visit Jane Hollins Nicholas, daughter of Wilson Cary Nicholas and the future wife of T.J. Randolph (on March 16, 1815); apparently the family was upset about remarks that Mrs. Nicholas had supposedly made about Martha Randolph and Ann Bankhead]
- Peter Carr to Mary Carr, 1814 Jun 25 (Box Box 1)
  [writes concerning her trip to Winchester]
- Jane B. Cary to Mary Carr, 1815 Jan 9 (Box Box 1)
  [hopes that Peter Carr's health has improved, tells of difficulties on her journey home, the anxiety of William Newsum over the sale of his Tennessee lands, requests Virginia [Terrell] (1798-1816) to write, mentions the pregnancy of Virginia Randolph Cary (with Archibald Cary, born March 9th) and the fatal sore throat prevalent around King William County]
- Mary Randolph Harrison (1773-?) to Mrs. Virginia Cary (1786- 1852), 1815 Jan 21 (Box Box 1)
  [answers her letter to Jane (Cary Harrison) who is away, makes arrangements to complete the bonnet to be sent to Mrs. Cocke, and reports that both she and her husband, Jane, and Lucy have all been sick]
- Judith Randolph (1772-1816) to her sister, Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1816 Feb 23 (Box Box 1)
  [refers to the death of her son, Theodoric Randolph (1794?-1815) and the burdens she bears alone; mentions the possible visit of her sister, Harriet]
- Mary Randolph Harrison to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1816 Apr 7 (Box Box 1)
  [refers to the death of Judith Randolph (1772-1816), sister of Virginia Cary, and her childhood friend, and the plans of Judith's son, John St. George Randolph (1792-1857), to build at "Bizarre" and her uncertainty if his uncle, John Randolph of Roanoke, will care for him or not]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [1817?] Apr 19 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses her financial situation, mentions James Overton Carr and his wife, Mary Minor, lists the names of the slaves that she sent to Mr. Kelly's, and warns against early marriage]
- Dabney S. Carr to George P. Stevenson, 1817 Oct 9 (Box Box 1)
  [explains why his trunk did not arrive and promises to see it off the next Saturday from Charlottesville, mentions the death of Colonel John Mercer, and the accident of Mr. Battaille]
- George P. Stevenson to Dabney S. Carr, 1817 Oct 28 (Box Box 1)
  [wants to get their mother to come to Baltimore and see the surgeon, Dr. Gibson, for her hearing, and tell her about the opportunity for Dabney to work in the insurance office of Uncle Hollins, where he serves as President, and Dabney can continue his studies at night]
- Dabney S. Carr to George P. Stevenson, 1817 Oct 31 (Box Box 1)
  [Hetty Carr will set off for Baltimore by the end of the week, and Uncle Samuel Carr hopes to take John A. Carr to Washington to either sail on the Franklin or join the navy, hopefully with a recommendation from Thomas Jefferson]
- Hetty Carr to George P. Stevenson, 1817 Nov 3 (Box Box 1)
  [did not leave on Saturday because Sam persuaded her to stay for a later stage which was unable to leave because the water was to high, will bring Maria with her to Baltimore, Dabney is delighted to remain there, and notes that Thomas Jefferson did not receive George's letter as soon as he should have, but will send a recommendation to Washington for John A. Carr]
- George P. Stevenson to Dabney S. Carr & Maria Carr, 1817 Dec 19 (Box Box 1)
  [sends a letter of brotherly advice]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, in care of John Hollins, 1817 Dec 21 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses family and financial affairs, W. Patterson and W. Gilmer will board with her next year, Mr. Craven wants to purchase the slave, Elizabeth, and Hetty Carr's property]
- Ellen P. Carr & Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1817 Dec 29 (Box Box 1)
  [names the servants they now have, including Anderson, Betsy Anne, and Robert; Jim is hired out to Richard Martin; cannot find white flour in Richmond, and they miss Dabney and Maria]
- John A. Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Jan 3 (Box Box 1)
  [full of friendly joking but little news]
- Ellen P. Carr & Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Jan 28 (Box Box 1)
  [cousin James is building a house, and cousin Martha comes to Carrsbrook every Friday for Ellen to say her lessons, which she describes; Jefferson [Randolph] came by last Sunday and thought Carrsbrook better off than when Hetty left Virginia, he has rented two plantations and 70-80 slaves from his grandfather, Thomas Jefferson, and gives him produce in return]
- George P. Stevenson to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Feb 5 (Box Box 1)
  [writing from Havana, Cuba, instructs Dabney to purchase Commercial & Farmers Bank stock for Eliza and his children, dividing the balance between himself and Maria]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Feb 15 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses financial situation and her desire to sell the plantation, prices of slaves are very high, hopes to eventually live in Baltimore with all her family together]
- John A. Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Feb 22 (Box Box 1)
  [letter from a childhood friend]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [1818] Mar 1 (Box Box 1)
  [worries about selling Carrsbrook, and the education of her girls]
- George P. Stevenson to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Mar 2 (Box Box 1)
  [writes from Havana with business and other instructions]
- O.M.C. & [T.?]L.M., to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Mar 6 (Box Box 1)
  [letter from two unknown childhood friends, teasing him about marriage]
- John A. Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Mar 9 (Box Box 1)
  [mentions his father and Doctor Everet as candidates for the General Assembly]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [1818] Mar 12 (Box Box 1)
  [urges him to tell her how Eliza and Maria are getting along and asks how Eliza is treating both of them while George is in Cuba]
- Mary Randolph Harrison to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1818 Mar 15 (Box Box 1)
  [mentions the illness of her husband, the visit of William Fitzhugh Randolph, her daughter Jane Cary Randolph and her trouble with her pregnancy, and Lucy Bolling Randolph, and the visit of General [John Hartwell Cocke?] to her husband]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [1818] Mar 22 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses finances with him, including the possibility of Mr. Kelly buying the plantation and slaves, and her hopes of moving to Baltimore and reuniting the family]
- Mary Randolph Harrison to Mrs. Virginia Cary, 1818 Mar 30 (Box Box 1)
  [regrets that she was unable to stop and see her when they returned from "Bremo," her daughter Jane suffers a miscarriage, and cousin Mary Irving sends her love to Virginia; also includes genealogical notes by another writer on the letter]
- George P. Stevenson to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Apr 1 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses business matters and moral instruction]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [1818] Apr 6 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses the condition of her crops this year, the unwillingness of Mr. Kelly to pay what she believes the plantation and slaves are worth, the necessity of being careful financially, availability of flour at Mr. Peyton's in Richmond for Eliza, and her concern for Maria's use of her time]
- Hetty Carr to Maria Carr, [1818] Apr 6 (Box Box 1)
  [gives her advice, warns her not to try to keep up with her friends, Mary T. and Alicia McBlair in fashion, and her trouble with one of her boarders]
- George P. Stevenson to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Apr 19 (Box Box 1)
  [writes from Cuba, discussing financial affairs]
- Hetty Carr to Maria Jefferson Carr, [1818] May 3 (Box Box 1)
  [asks her to account for the spending of her one hundred dollars, and insists that she gets her teeth filled]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 May 3 (Box Box 1)
  [Eliza has written to her, unreconciled to George remaining in Cuba on business, her concerns about Dabney & Maria, if Eliza should leave Baltimore to join him there, and the condition of the plantation]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [1818] May 23 (Box Box 1)
  [her concerns about where Dabney and Maria will board if Eliza and her family go to the Charity School, suggests that Robert Smith may ask them to stay with him, worries about who will care for her children, Maria, Hollins, and Jane Margaret, should she die before they are grown, or before Dabney is married]
- Ellen B. Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 May 24 (Box Box 1)
  [writes during her stay in Richmond, mentions the publication of William Wirt's biography of Patrick Henry, and discusses her improvement in dancing]
- John A. Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 May 24 (Box Box 1)
  [letter from childhood friend]
- Uncle Dabney Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 May 28 (Box Box 1)
  [promises to get General [John George] Jackson, who is on the spot, to investigate his deed to lands on Cedar Creek, near Clarksburg, [West Virginia] and begs his nephew to write to him about his welfare]
- Hetty Carr to Maria Jefferson Carr, [1818] May 31 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses family affairs, her pleasure that Maria has filled her teeth, and Dabney Minor handling the sale of Carrsbrook and her slaves in Fairfax]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [1818] Jun 18 (Box Box 1)
  [Jefferson and Jane Randolph dined with her at "Dunlora," James [Carr?] has lost a child, and mentions the Trists]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Jun 25 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses the prospects of selling Carrsbrook again]
- General J[ohn] G[eorge] Jackson (1777-1825) to Judge Dabney Carr, 1818 Jun 30 (Box Box 1)
  [reports on his efforts to locate a deed to the land on Cedar Creek conveyed by General Smith to Dabney S. Carr]
- James O. Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Jul 4 (Box Box 1)
  [his friend and relative discusses the crops on the farm at Carrsbrook and the arrival of Maria there]
- John A. Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Jul 7 (Box Box 1)
  [saw Jane Smith and Mary Taylor in Winchester]
- Dabney Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Jul 9 (Box Box 1)
  [Aunt Betsy is very unwell, encloses the letter from General Jackson (see June 30, 1818)]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [1818] Jul 18 (Box Box 1)
  [discusses the wheat harvest, the birth of George P. Stevenson's son, and the intention of James Carr to buy Carrsbrook, if he is able to sell his own place]
- Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, [1818] Jul 19 (Box Box 1)
  [further discussions of the intention of James & Mary Carr to buy Carrsbrook, if he is able to sell his own place, and has found the deed to Dabney's land on Cedar Creek, West Virginia]
- Ellen Carr & Hetty Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Jul 30 (Box Box 1)
  [further discussions of the intention of James & Mary Carr to buy Carrsbrook]
- James O. Carr to Dabney S. Carr, 1818 Aug 2 (Box Box 1)